Guide to the Joseph Barrell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joseph Barrell papers
1909-1920
MS 778
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Correspondence, the manuscript for "The Piedmont terraces of the Northern Appalachians" in various stages, notes and miscellaneous items on geology originating during Barrell's service as secretary of the geological faculty at Yale University. The correspondence largely relates to university matters, except for that with Henry H. Robinson which pertains to the article.
Barrell, Joseph, 1869-1919
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Barrell Papers consist of correspondence and manuscript material dating from 1909-1920. The correspondence is from Barrell's years at Yale (1903-1919) and is related primarily to his position as secretary of the geological faculty (1908-1919). Included among the manuscripts are Barrell's draft for his article "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians," and Henry H. Robinson's notes for editing the article.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Barrell, geologist and engineer, was born in New Providence, New Jersey, on December 15, 1869. He received a B.S. degree from Lehigh University in 1892 and a mining engineer (E.M.) degree the following year. From 1893 to 1897, Barrell was an instructor in mining and metallurgy at Lehigh and was awarded his M.S. degree in 1897. He received his Ph.D.from Yale University in 1900. That same year Barrell returned to Lehigh as an assistant professor of geology and chairman of the department of natural sciences. He left in 1903 to become assistant professor of geology at Yale. Barrell was appointed Professor of Structural Geology in 1908 and Silliman Memorial Lecturer from 1917 to 1918. Barrell was secretary of the Yale geological faculty from 1908 to 1919. Shortly before his death on May 4, 1919, Barrell was elected to the National Academy of Sciences.
Geology; Science; Educators; Geologists; Mining engineers; Barrell, Joseph, 1869-1919; Robinson, Henry Hollister, 1873-1925; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Geology and Geophysics
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1909-1919
    - A-W (Box 1, Folder 1 - 15)
  - Yale University, Geology Department: course descriptions, correspondence, memoranda, and government notices, 1911-1918 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Circular concerning thirteenth annual intercollegiate excursion of New England, 1915 October 15-16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Outlines of paper and speech on "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians", 1912 December 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript copy of "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians," with some notes by Henry R. Robinson, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Author's proof of "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians" and related papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Henry Hollister Robinson's TS annotated copy of "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians", [ca. 1919] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Page proof of "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians" as edited by H. Robinson, for publication in the, 1920 April (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence between Henry H. Robinson and E. W. Shaw, of the U.S. Geological Society, 1919 December 24-26 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Henry H. Robinson concerning cost, figures, estimates, and notes for publication of "The Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians", undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Abstract of "Piedmont Terraces of the Northern Appalachians and their Mode of Origin;" abstract of "Post-jurassic history of the Northern Appalachians", undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Abstracts of remarks in reply by Joseph Barrell before the Geological Society of America, 1912 December 30 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notes and rough drafts of figures to be used as illustrations, 1913-1918 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Geological notebook with entries for Maryland, 1912 and New York, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 29)